Guide to the Costume Ball Photograph Collection 1875-1932 PR 223
New-York Historical Society
Costume Ball photograph collection
1875-1932
New-York Historical Society
PR 223
1.26 Linear feet (3 boxes)
Collection of photographs and mounted clippings portraying society notables in costumes for a variety of New York balls held between 1875 and 1932. The majority of the photographs portray attendees of the 1883 Vanderbilt Ball.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Costume Ball Photograph Collection has been compiled from a variety of gifts. The majority of the collection came as a gift from Harold Seton in 1927. Other gifts include those of George C.D. Odell in 1928, Mrs. John H. Coster in 1933, Mrs. F.R. Appleton in 1941, Henry V. Warner in 1944, and Mrs. William R. Stewart in 1977.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in six series:
Series I: Beaux-Arts Balls
Series II: Bradley Martin Ball
Series III: Delmonico Ball
Series IV: Hewitt Ball
Series V: Vanderbilt Ball
Series VI: Miscellaneous and Unidentified Balls
Historical Note
The Costume Ball Photograph Collection consists of photographs and some mounted clippings portraying members of high society in costume for a variety of balls held in New York City between 1875 and 1932. The majority of the collection came as a gift from Harold Seton, a theater enthusiast and prominent collector of photographs of stage celebrities, politicians, and upper class notables.
Most of the photographs in this collection were taken by Mora, the studio of Josè Maria Mora, a Cuban refugee who moved to the United States in 1868 and opened a photography studio in 1870. Mora was an extremely popular portrait studio in the closing decades of the nineteenth century; it was especially well known for its specialization in theatrical portraits and its wide range of elaborate theatrical backdrops and props.
Related Materials
Additional photograph of costume balls and individuals in costume are also available in the Portrait File (PR 52). An album of vintage photographs of attendees at the Vanderbilt Ball of 1883 is available in the Album File (PR 2-282), as is an album of modern copy prints of photographs of attendees of the Bradley Martin Ball of 1897 (PR 2-264).
Scope and Contents
The Costume Ball Photograph Collection spans the period from 1875 to 1932 and primarily contains portraits, in the form of photographs or mounted clippings, of society notables in attendance at New York costume balls. The collection is arranged alphabetically by the common name of each ball, and thereunder by name of sitter. Groups are filed under one individual's name with cross references provided under other sitters' names. Unidentified balls are filed at the end of the collection. In general, women are listed under their final married names, with first and maiden names following when known. Photographs are assumed to have been taken close to the date of each ball; for clippings, publication dates are given.
Cabinet photographs.; Clippings (information artifacts); Photographic prints.; Portraits.; Programs (documents); New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; Balls (Parties).; Costume -- New York (State) -- New York.; Upper class -- Clothing.; Upper class -- New York (State) -- New York.; Astor family; Belmont (Family); Hewitt family; Vanderbilt family; Beaux-Arts Institute of Design; Delmonico's Restaurant (New York, N.Y.); Martin, Bradley; Mora, 1849-1926
- Series I: Beaux-Arts Ball
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I consists of twelve mounted, captioned clippings from the January 31, 1932 New York Times, documenting the costumes of some notable attendees of the annual ball given by the Society of Beaux-Arts Architects in the Waldorf-Astoria Hotel. The 1932 ball was themed "A Pageant of Old New York and the First Inaugural Ball of the United States of America," and the several thousand elites attending wore ancestral costumes or reproductions dating from the colonial period through 1789.
  - Alford, June, 1932 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Boomer, Mr. and Mrs. Lucius (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    See: Chrysler, Mr. and Mrs. Walter
  - Butterfield, Millie, 1932 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chrysler, Mr. and Mrs. Walter with Mr. and Mrs. Lucius Boomer, 1932 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Davisson, Mrs. Richard L., 1932 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Degnon, Ann, 1932 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - De Rham, Mrs. H. Casimir (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    See: Wilmerding, E. Coster
  - Hobson, Lucia, 1932 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Menken, Mrs. S. Stanwood, 1932 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Schuster, Betty, 1932 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Sheedy, Eleanor, 1932 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Snell, Mr. and Mrs. Lawrence W., 1932 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Warburton, W. John and Ruth Jones, 1932 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Wilmerding, E. Coster and Mrs. H. Casimir De Rham, 1932 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Bradley Martin Ball
  Series II consists of a few portraits, a mounted clipping, and a copy photograph of a Harper's Weekly illustration of a scene at the controversial ball given by Bradley and Cornelia Sherman Martin at the Waldorf Hotel on February 10, 1897. Thrown during an economic depression, the event drew wide criticism from those who thought it an ostentatious display of wealth and excess. Chief among the critics was Reverend Dr. William S. Rainsford, rector of St. George's Protestant Episcopal Church, who sparked a frenzy in the press after criticizing the event on the pulpit and reportedly advising his parishioners not to attend. His statements spurred a public debate on the best use of wealth in society, with prominent public figures weighing in on the issue. The only vintage photograph of a guest in costume for this ball is a portrait of William Beekman by Gilbert Studios.
  - Beekman, James William, 1897 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Childs, Jennie Clark, 1931 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Copy photograph of a Harper's Weekly illustration, by Harry W. McVickar of crowd scene at the Bradley Martin Ball, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
- Series III: Delmonico Ball
  Series III consists of a group of sixteen photographs depicting attendees of an unidentified costume party labeled as being the Delmonico Ball of 1875. A variety of events were held at Delmonico's in 1875, the favorite restaurant and party venue of New York society in the Gilded Age. It is unclear which of the 1875 events the photographs in this collection depict. All photographs in this series were donated by Harold Seton. Included are a few mounted clippings from a later piece on the Harold Seton collection in the New York Herald Tribune in October 25, 1927.
  - Bacon, Martha Cowdin and her sister Katherine Cowdin Marquand, 1875 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Barnwell, Mrs. Morgan C., 1931 Oct. 25 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    [mounted Herald Tribune clipping]
  - Borland, Constance Rives and Maude Rives Smith, 1875 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chanler, Minnie Ashley, 1931 Oct. 25 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Douglas, Adelaide Townsend (3), 1931 Oct. 25 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    [1 is a mounted Herald Tribune clipping]
  - Jay, William and Consuelo Yznaga, 1875 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Kemys, Mrs. Edward, 1875 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Marquand, Katherine Cowdin (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    See: Bacon, Martha Cowdin
  - Paget, Minnie Stevens (2), 1875 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Post, Charles, 1875 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Redmond, Helen, 1875 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sands, E. Louise, 1875 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Smith, Maude Rives (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    See: Borland, Constance Rives
  - Townsend, Betty, 1875 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Whitney, Edith May and Carrie May Wright, 1875 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Wright, Carrie May (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    See: Whitney, Edith May
  - Yznaga, Consuelo (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    See: Jay, William
- Series IV: Hewitt Ball
  Series IV consists of photographs depicting guests wearing antique costumes at an event given by Sarah Cooper Hewitt and her daughters, Sarah and Eleanor, in 1908. Mrs. Peter Cooper Hewitt is portrayed in a ball gown originally worn at the Prince of Wales Ball in 1860, and the Vicomte de Périgny is portrayed in wedding clothing dating from 1845. Also included with these photographs is a program for the French plays performed at this event in the Hewitt's private theater, including Guy de Maupassant's Histoire du Viéux Temps and Eugène Verconsin's Qûete à Domicile.
  - Vicomte de Périgney, Mrs. Peter Cooper Hewitt, and an unidentified man in costumes worn at the Prince of Wales Ball in 1860 and a man's wedding costume from 1845, 1908 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Program, 1908 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
- Series V: Vanderbilt Ball
  Series V comprises the bulk of the Costume Ball Collection; included are more than 150 portraits of attendees in costume for the fancy dress ball given by William K. and Alva Smith Vanderbilt in their newly built home at 600 Fifth Avenue on March 26, 1883. At the time, the ball was considered to be one of the most "lavish" in New York City's history. It featured guests dressed as courtiers, witches, royalty, godesses, and opera and nursery rhyme characters. Quadrilles were performed by guests dressed according to particular themes.
  Included in this series are photographs of members of many of the elite families of New York, including the Astors, the Belmonts, and the Vanderbilts. Portraits in this series are almost exclusively the work of Mora, and include a variety of that studio's fanciful backdrops and props. The hostess, Alva Smith Vanderbilt (later Alva Belmont), is portrayed as a Venetian princess with a palatial background, surrounded by flying doves. Constance Rives Borland, dressed as a bee with protruding wings and antennae, is set against a convincing woodland background, and Grace Stebbins Chapin seems to dip her hand into a flower-strewn pond. Caroline Seward Endicott stands in a faux snowstorm with her hands tucked into a fur muff. Most of the photographs in this series bear brief identifications on the verso, and some also identify the costume or the quadrille in which the individual was featured.
  - Alexandre, John E., 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Appleton, Fanny, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Appleton, Francis R. (2), 1932 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bacon, Martha W. Cowdin, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - Baldwin, Natalie, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - Beach, Frederick O., one with Caroline Kean Rives (2), 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - Beckwith, Helen, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - Belmont, Alva Smith (1853-1933) (3) [while Mrs. W.K. Vanderbilt], 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Belmont, Mrs. August, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Belmont, Perry, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Benkard, Fanny G. Horton (2), 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Beresford, Jack, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Blacque, Kate Reed, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Blake, Kate, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Blake, Daisy, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bliss, Fancy Johnson (2), 1883, 1927 Mar. 26 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    [1 is a mounted clipping]
  - Borland, Constance Rives, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bridgham, Honorine Garguilo, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Burnett, Agnes Suffern Tailer (2), 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chapin, Grace Stebbins, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Clews, Lucy M. Worthington (2), 1883, 1927 Mar. 26 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Clift, Bessie, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cowdin, John Elliot, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cram, Henry, 1927 Mar. 26 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
    [mounted clipping]
  - Cruger, Julie G. Storrow, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - Douglas, William P., 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
  - Eldridge, Mrs., 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Endicott, Caroline Seward, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Endicott, Mary Louise Thoron, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Fales, Samuel, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Francklyn, Reginald with Agnes Binsse Francklyn, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Furman, John (2), 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Furness, Clementina, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Gambrill, Anna Van Nest (2), 1883, 1927 Mar. 26 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Garner, Mrs. W.G., 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Gurnee, Augustus Coe, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Haig, Charlotte Augusta Astor, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - Henderson, Hildegard Oelrichs, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - Hewitt, Lucy Work, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - Hillhouse, Georgiana D. Remsen, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - Howland, Frederika Belmont, 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - Howland, Gardiner G., Jr., 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - Hoyt, William S., 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - Hunt, Mrs. Richard M., 1883 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - Kane, Annie Schermerhorn, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
  - Kean, Elizabeth, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
  - Kean, Hamilton Fish (3), 1883, 1927 Mar. 26 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
  - Kean, Julian H., 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
  - Kennard, Cora Smith (2), 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
  - Kernochan, Mary Whitney, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
  - Kessler, Ada P. Smith, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
  - Kountze, Annie P. Ward (3), 1883, 1927 Mar. 26 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19)
  - Lamson, John L., 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
  - Lawrence, John, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
  - Lawrence, Mrs. John (2), 1883, 1927 Mar. 26 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
  - Lawrence, May K. Bird (3), 1883, 1927 Mar. 26 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
  - Lawley, Annie Cunard, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
  - Lee, Cornelius (2), 1883, 1927 Mar. 26 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
  - Lee, Mattie Blood, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
  - Lee, Sarah Hoyt, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
  - Le Roy, Eleanor, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
  - Levitt, Mrs. H., 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
  - Mallory, Jean Turnure, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
  - Marié, Peter, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
  - Martin, Bradley, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
  - McClellan, Georgiana Heckscher, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
  - Mesier, Miss, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
  - Moore, Ridgeway, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
  - Morgan, Emma Leavitt (2), 1883, 1927 Mar. 20 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
  - Navarro, Antonio de, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
  - Neilson, Frederic, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
  - Norrie, Eloise Lawrence Breese (2), 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
  - Northcote, Edith Livingston Fish, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
  - Olin, Elise Barlow (2), 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 25)
  - Otis, Mrs. James (2), 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 25)
  - Paget, Minnie Stevens, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 26)
  - Parsons, Elizabeth Webb, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 26)
  - Parsons, Mary L. (3), 1883, 1927 Mar. 26 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 26)
  - Peters, Charles Grenville, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27)
  - Pierson, Augusta Rhodes, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27)
  - Post, Marie de Trobriand, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27)
  - Potter, Cora Urquhart, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27)
  - Rasin, Ignaz, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 28)
  - Redmond, Roland, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 28)
  - Redmond, Helen, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 28)
  - Ripley, Sidney Dillon, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 28)
  - Rives, Caroline Kean (Offsite-box 2, Folder 28)
    See: Beach, Frederick O.
  - Rives, George L., 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 28)
  - Robbins, Lizzie Pelham Bend (2), 1883, 1927 Mar. 26 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 29)
  - Rogers, Anne C. Coleman, 1883 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 29)
  - Schenck, Mary L. Stone, 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 30)
  - Seward, Alice D. (2), 1883, 1927 Mar. 26 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 30)
  - Shepard, Margaret Louisa Vanderbilt, 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 30)
  - Sloane, Jessie Robbins, 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 30)
  - Speyer, Ellin Price, 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 31)
  - Stevens, Marietta Reed, 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 31)
  - Strong, Ella, 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 31)
  - Terry, Mrs. Antonio, 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 32)
  - Thayer, Dora, 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 32)
  - Thompson, Frederick Diodate (2), 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 32)
  - Townsend, Amy, 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 33)
  - Townsend, Eugenie M. Gibert, 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 33)
  - Twombly, Florence Vanderbilt (2), 1883, 1927 Mar. 26 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 33)
  - Vanderbilt, Alice G., 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 34)
  - Vanderbilt, Alva Smith (Offsite-box 3, Folder 34)
    See: Belmont, Alva Smith
  - Wagstaff, Mary Barnard, 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 35)
  - Walsh, Marie Blood, 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 35)
  - Warren, Alice Binsse, 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 35)
  - Webb, Lila Osgood Vanderbilt, 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 36)
  - Welles, Frances Swan (2), 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 36)
  - White, Emily Vanderbilt (3), 1883, 1927 Mar. 26 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 37)
  - Whiting, Sallie (2), 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 37)
  - Whitney, Edith May (3), 2 are with sister Carrie May Wright, 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 37)
  - Whitney, Miss, 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 37)
  - Willing, Arthur, 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 38)
  - Wilmerding, Margaret, 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 38)
  - Wilson, Caroline Schermerhorn Astor, 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 38)
  - Winthrop, Buchanan (2), 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 38)
  - Winthrop, Sarah Townsend, 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 38)
  - Woolsey, Miss, 1883 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 38)
  - Wright, Carrie May (Offsite-box 3, Folder 38)
  - Ball scenes - negative reprint from Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, dated April 7, 1883, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 39)
- Series VI: Miscellaneous and Unidentified
  Series VI contains photographs of people in costume for unidentified or unspecific parties or costume balls. It includes a folder of six group portraits, including one at Dr. Strong's Santitarium in Saratoga Springs, New York, dated 1896, and one undated portrait identified as a group at Sharon Springs, New York. Photographs are arranged alphabetically by sitter, with unidentified group portraits at the end of the series.
  - Cornican, Miss (?), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 40)
  - Gurnee, Augustus Coe, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 40)
  - Livingston, Mrs., undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 40)
  - Norrie, Eloise L. (2), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 40)
  - Northcote, Edith Fish, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 40)
  - Paget, Minnie Stevens (2), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 40)
  - Rogers, Miss, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 40)
  - Rutherford, Miss, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 40)
  - Schack, Miss, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 40)
  - Townsend, Amy, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 40)
  - Webb, Frances Swan, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 40)
  - Unidentified individuals (2), undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 40)
  - Unidentified groups, 1893, 1896, undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 40)